What I want to do today is um give an
overview of this class. Uh I'm I'm
actually curious before we get started.
Um this is now September 2025. Um how
many of you you know just started at
Stanford? Raise your hand. Wow. Cool.
Awesome. So others pay attention to who
just raise their hands and do say hi to
them and you know help welcome all the
people they just joined Stanford in
whatever program. Um, CS230 is a class
that we offer in the flipped classroom
format. And what that means is that
instead of listening to me or Kan uh my
co-instructor that you meets that you
meet next week, instead of listening to
us lecture at you for an hour, R 20
minutes or whatever, um we actually ask
you to watch a lot of the video lectures
online so that we can then make use of
the precious in-classroom time for much
richer, deeper discussions. So both
today and for the entire quarter um I
would really warmly welcome anyone
raising questions uh raise your hand and
in fact I I I find that um instead of
you sitting there oh even though we have
a longer session scheduled by the
registra uh we'll use usually only up to
an hour and 20 minutes for this course.
Um and the goal is to it turns out that
a lot of Stanford students were watching
you know the lectures um on uh sego or
on the online videos anyway. So rather
than us delivering that lecture, same
lecture year after year, we put a lot
more effort to put very high quality
lecture videos online and we'll ask you
to just watch that online which people
are doing anyway but just highly editive
offline watching um spend and spend the
classroom time you know doing the things
that make sense for us to get together
in person too. Um so because you haven't
watched any of the lectures yet or I
assume most of you have not today we'll
even maybe have a slightly shorter
session to introduce the class talk over
logistics and so on right um as many of
you know deep learning is one of the
latest hottest trends technologies of
computer science and AI um if we look at
you know say our PhD emissions or or
even mast's emissions a very large
fraction of all students that come to
Stanford or applying to come to Stanford
want to work on AI, right? I'm not sure
I'm allowed to say the numbers, but they
are, you know, extremely high, um, as
you can imagine. And so, uh, my goal and
my my co-instructor Ken's goals, our
collective goal is through this quarter
to help you get to near or at pretty
much state-of-the-art with regard to
deep learning. um and make sure that all
of you walk away from this class highly
skilled at applying deep learning. Um
and so
it turns out that a lot of progress in
AI over the last I don't know decade
maybe 10 15 years was made by scaling
and one of the reasons why deep learning
was so successful was because it's good
at absorbing a lot of data. So
you know if I draw a figure where on the
x-axis I plot the amount of data
we have for a problem um then using more
traditional machine learning algorithms
so you know logistic regression maybe
decision trees using all the generations
of AI machine learning algorithms um
as you gave it more and more data the
performance or the accuracy of the more
traditional algorithms would plateau,
right? It was as if. So take speech
recognition with older generations of
algorithms, even as you fed it more and
more data, hundreds and thousands and
tens of thousands of hours of speech
data, the accuracy would often plateau
and it was as if the older generations
of algorithms didn't know what to do
with all the data that we now have. But
what we start to find about 10 15 years
ago um was that if you train a small
neuronet network also known as a small
deep learning model this performance
would kind of maybe get better and
better. And if you train a medium-sized
one and if you train a very large
neon network the performance just keeps
getting better and better. And I think
the reason that deep learning has
dominated the AI scene for the last 10
15 years is because there is a recipe
for training very large neuronet
networks um that we can then shove a lot
of data into that results in exceptional
performance. So I think um we started to
see this uh because of some frankly some
Stanford research papers um about 15
years ago when when you know did the
first early work on using cuder
programming and GPUs to scale up deep
learning. Uh oh by the way actually has
one fun fact um uh the first my first uh
GPU machine used to train neuronet
networks using crew there which is a
controversial thing at the time. It was
built by a Stanford undergrad in his
dorm room. Right. His name was Ian
Goodfellow. But um I think that compute
server built in a Stanford undergrad
dorm room. Um allowed us at Sanford to
lay the early foundations of using CUDAR
a time a modern language for training
GPUs to train large neuronet networks
and then you know obviously that
influenced a lot of people and helped
scaling up deep learning take off. So I
I I tell that story because um sometimes
the work that some of you can do you
know in a dorm room or graduate house
student housing or whatever or in a lab
at Stanford um uh looking back over some
number of years it can really have a
huge impact and maybe in this class some
of you will do work um as impactful as
that someday as well. But so what we
start to find was that as you train
larger and larger neuronet networks they
could soak up lots of data and drive
exceptional performance. Um and then
there was a research paper out of bu
which showed that as you scale up
neuronet networks as you scale up deep
learning algorithms the performance
gains are actually quite predictable. So
you can forecast if you buy this many
GPUs throw this much comput and this
much data at it what would the
performance be? Um and then later open
AAI popularized the idea with a really
influential paper on scaling laws. Um
and that predictability of how deep
learning gets better in performance then
drove a lot of the investments uh in you
know data centers and and building very
large AI models with lots of data. Um
and so
let's see in terms of where this class
sits. So in computer science all of us
build on each other's work right a lot
of the way that uh computer science and
AI has made progress is we build on top
of other ideas that are in turn built on
top of other ideas that in turn they in
turn built on top of other ideas. So
maybe I want to give you a little map to
to to show you maybe where deep learning
sits. Um so I think there are
you know machine learning is built on
top of computer science. So I think it's
actually helpful to learn CS
fundamentals. And even though I use I
suspect vast majority of use AI assisted
coding be it tools like cloud code or
Gemini CLI or open codeex or cursor or
wind surf or whatever. Um I find that
people that know CS fundamentals that
really understand computer science uh
that really understand how computers
work rather than like I'm going to vibe
code this you know like when you
understand CS fundamentals you get
things to work much better but on top of
CS fundamentals
there's a set of um
machine learning skills.
So how do you build algorithms that can
learn from data? Um and then deep
learning is a special type of machine
learning. Well, that's really the most
effective type of machine learning as
far as I can tell in which we train
neuronet networks. We train certain
types of algorithms to learn from large
amounts of data. Uh so far in the last
10 minutes, you probably heard me use
the words deep learning and neuronet
networks. And I think today those two
terms are almost interchangeable. Uh
some some purists will insist on some
technical differences. Raw practice
doesn't mean the same thing. But what
happened was the term neonet networks
had been around for decades. But around
10 15 years ago a number of us realized
that you know deep learning it was just
a much better brand. Um, and so even
though neuronet networks have been
around for decades, starting about 1015
years ago, it was deep learning that
took off because who doesn't want
learning that is really deep, right?
It's just a good brand. Um, but you hear
me use those terms kind of
interchangeably, but um, deep learning
algorithms, neuronet networks, they give
us a way to take advantage of more and
more and more compute capacity. So they
can build very large AI models with a
lot of parameters to soak up the large
amounts of data to get more and more you
know intelligence or to make better and
better predictions or make generate more
and more accurate outputs using the
large amount of data that's available to
us. Ever since I was a teenager my mom's
been trying to convince me to stop
mumbling.
But now many years later I still
struggle with that. So I I'll I'll try
my best. So please uh um wave at me or
or kind of uh let me know if I start to
drift lower again. Yeah. All right. My I
think um uh my mother would be very
happy that to practice like this now.
Um all right. So CS fundamentals,
machine learning, deep learning, and
then the recent generative AI
revolution.
You know, generative AI um sorry bad
handwriting. generative AI um which is
mostly built by a specific type of
neuronet network called a transformer
neuronet network which you learn about
in this class. to actually learn what is
the transformer architecture um later in
this quarter as well is in turn built on
top of deep learning right so I assume
all of you you know are regularly
prompting OM large language models to
help you get work done um and what I
find is that while I use OM all the time
for a lot of applications just prompting
LMS it doesn't cut it there are a lot of
things that I cannot get to work just by
prompting an OM um and so often have to
go a layer deeper into the deep learning
layer of abstraction and fiddle with
deep learning algorithms in order to get
certain things to work. And in fact, so
what this class covers is we'll try to
make sure that you are, you know, expert
near expert in deep learning by the end
of this class, but we'll also um kind of
dip a little bit into machine learning
concepts. So we'll talk a lot about
objective functions and tips and tricks
for optimizing parameters in efficient
way. Um and then we'll also actually
reach up a little bit to cover some Gen
AI. In particular, we'll talk about what
is the transformer network. And then
through this quarter, Ken and I will
also chat a little bit about the um job
landscape as relates to Gen AI and deep
learning and how to use how how deep
learning is enabling certain types of
Genai applications. Okay. Um,
I have more to say about this, but let
me just pause for a second and see if
you have any questions.
>> Yeah, go for it.
>> Oh, good question. What I say prerequ
um, congratulations. You've won the
prize for the first question asked in
CS230 2035. So, well done.
Yeah. Um, so is machine learning a
prerect to this course? Uh, not really.
So I think two common entry points to AI
at Stanford are um CS well a few common
entry points are CS129 CS229 and CS230.
Um if you don't know any machine
learning this course may end up going a
little bit fast may seem like it's going
a little bit fast in the first uh I
don't know two or three weeks but some
people do pick things up quickly that
way. uh and um maybe a screen. So a few
causes that you may hear about. Um
so 129 is a relatively easy entry point
into machine learning that slow tends to
you takes a longer time to go through
the core concepts of machine learning
like what's optimization objective? How
do you implement gradient descent? What
is um logistic regression? What's a very
basic neural network? So this is a
relatively applied easiest of the of of
of this list. Um CS229 which I'm also
involved in co-eing is uh much more
mathematical and theoretical very high
pace very intense and very mathematical
and this is less applied than 129 and
230 but this will go over um a lot more
of the theory and the math derivations
behind machine learning algorithms. So
for example, if you ever want to learn
how to do um calculus not using row
numbers but calculus using matrices and
vectors, you know, that's a bunch of
sort of I don't know mildly complex math
that's worth knowing. Um CS229 goes over
that. CS230, this class is relatively
applied and it focuses just on deep
learning. So of all the machine
learning, there are a lot of machine
learning algorithms out there, right?
learning, unsuized learning, a lot of
machine learning algorithms out there
and many many of them are very useful
but and and so they're all worth
learning about but of all the machine
learning algorithms out there the one
category that is most useful is you know
that's taken off the most is deep
learning and this class focuses just on
that but the other arms also worth
learning about. So 129 is the easiest on
ramp. Um but if you've done either 229
or 230, I would probably skip 129 at
that point. But if you are getting
started there there are multiple on
ramps.
>> Yeah.
>> Can we take 229 and 230 together or do
you think it's about
>> Oh uh yeah. Can you take 229 and 230 uh
together? Yep. Thank you. Price for the
second question.
Feel want to clap. Sure. Go for it.
[Applause]
Um yes, you can take CSU30 and CS29
together. Um we designed the two
curriculara to be relatively low in
overlap. So the very small amount of of
overlap between these two,
>> right? All right. We we won't clap for
every single question, but yeah, go
ahead.
>> Um are you going to cover more like
recent learning algorithms that are used
in recent lab?
>> Yeah. So will we cover the recent um OM
developments? We will touch on the
transformer neural network but um uh not
the uh latest OM variations in this
course. Um I think a lot of the it turns
out that when you go out to get a job
well maybe right if assuming you go and
work in industry the number of people
training LMS is actually very small
right so those jobs seem to be
incredibly well paid. We hear about kind
of very high salaries in news media, but
the vast majority of application
builders end up um sometimes working at
the geni level, not that often trading a
transformer from scratch. Um but then
often using deep learning tools as well.
So maybe one example um something that
many of my teams have done is um we have
trained transform model foundation
models from scratch but relatively small
ones in in say startups. But one thing
we do do quite a lot is um take a
pre-trained transformer network uh and
then engineer our own data to further
fine-tune it. Right? Uh sorry if I'm
using words that you may not totally
understand. You know pre-trained fine
tetun you know what all those terms are
by the end of this quarter. So those are
things that we actually do um uh kind of
day-to-day this is important for getting
a bunch of brothers work. So you will
gain the foundations needed to do type
of work in this course. Um the one thing
one thing we don't do is talk a lot
about how to train the largest cutting
edge transformer networks. I think that
is a very important skill set is a
relatively niche one for which some
people are you know getting paid really
really well but the number of people
doing that in the world is actually
small whereas the number of people
building applications with you know this
set of skills is is is very large. Do
>> you know any courses that you cover?
>> Uh do I know any courses covering that?
I think Percy Leang was thinking about
doing something but I don't remember
he's doing it this quarter. Um few
people are think thinking about doing
something like that. Yeah.
>> Um this is a question about the course
itself. Um do you know what portion of
the course is going to involve like
mathematical analysis and what is
coding?
So um so I'm just repeating for the for
the um mic for the uh home viewers. What
portion is uh coding versus what
proportion is um mathematical analysis?
This course is relatively math light. Um
sorry maybe that was too strong a
statement but I think this this course
is very practical. Um I I I I remember
many years back I was speaking with a
mathematician.
Um and you know we were just chatting
and he was asking he was just talking
about his career why he chose to be a
mathematician and I I still remember you
know this he had he had like stars in
his eyes when he told me that he chose
his career path because he felt his role
is to pursue truth and beauty in the
universe and that's why he became a
mathematician.
In this course, I'm not going to do any
truth and beauty stuff, right? So,
um, truth and beauty is good, but you
find that I I want to take a very
practical approach to, um, talking about
how to build applications and build
software that works. Um, yeah, cool.
Anything else?
Right. Cool. Awesome. All right. Thank
you for all the questions. Please keep
them coming and feel free to interrupt
me or Kan throughout this quarter as
well with questions. I love it. Um so,
oh just to just to flesh this out a
little bit more, this is what I see in
terms of um teams building practical
applications. And I'm excited about
applications because with improving
machine learning algorithms, deep
learning algorithms, Jenny algorithms,
there are a lot of applications that you
can build now that just were, you know,
impossible or or like really
inaccessible, you know, to to any person
to build even a few years ago. Um, and
so I find that when I prompt Gen AI, it
works really well for a lot of textbased
applications. Um, and there's work on
multimodal LMS, large multimodal models.
So making inroads into vision, making
inrows into audio, but really genai
algorithms, especially transformer
networks trained to output text, you
know, like chipd claw, gemini, and so
on, really fantastic for textbased
applications, right? Um and I find
myself
um regularly working with deep learning
algorithms directly when I am working
with um audio data,
image and video data. Um and then also
um a lot of structured data.
Ah sorry my handwriting is awful. Right.
So uh structured data refers to large
tables of numbers right like giant you
know Excel or Google sheet spreadsheets
uh but so that's that's structured data
unstructured data refers to text audio
images maybe video um and because a lot
of genai right language models like chat
GBD had grown up being text in text out
kinds of um uh machines they are
remarkable for a lot of text processing
applications but for other types of data
I end up often and you know dipping down
directly to use various deep learning
algorithms. Um and then it turns out
that for textbased data if all you do is
prompting you could usually go quite
far. So a lot of applications are built
by prompting OM but um uh but I've been
on you know quite a few teams where
after fiddling with the prompts for a
month you just can't get the performance
to be better just by tuning the prompts.
Um or another good problem to have. It
turns out use of geni tools are
relatively inexpensive when you're
prototyping, right? It's like you know a
few dollars per million tokens. You can
do a lot. Um but sometimes if you're
lucky enough to be on a product that um
uh his product market fit and a lot of
users want to use, you know, multiple
times I've been on teams where we
basically did not care about our um uh
uh launch language model bill, right? It
was like whatever, you know, $20 a month
or $100 a month was fine. But when more
and more users start using it, then to
your team's kind of positive surprise,
your AI bill really starts to skyrocket.
And then at some point, you look at how
much you're paying for your AI bill for
the large language models. And um to
bend the cost curve back down, often lot
of the techniques in deep learning
become very relevant as well. So there
are I don't know, I'm thinking just some
of our bills were really breathtaking. I
don't want to say the numbers, which is
kind of definitely more than we want to
pay. You know, as much as we love the
companies providing OM, our bills that
were paying them were significantly
larger than I wanted to pay. Um, and
then knowing how to use deep learning to
fine-tune smaller models. That was
really the critical skill set that just
bent the cost curve back and just made
the whole thing affordable to keep on
providing a service. Right. So, um,
yeah. Right.
So that's what so that's the skill sets
I hope you get from this course.
Let's see.
All right. Um that was right
and um to give a
sorry use this one.
So to give a f to to give a quick um
overview this course the online
materials is broken down into five
modules. So just give you a overview of
the five of them. Uh first one is on the
basics of neuronet networks sorry NN
neuronet networks and uh DL deep
learning right. So you learn how to
build a neuronet network or deep
learning algorithm from scratch in
Python. Um I find that sometimes if you
use the frameworks like TensorFlow or
PyTorch it hides a lot of the details.
So we actually work through um how to
build a basic neuronet network and how
to build a basic deep learning algorithm
just in raw Python. So you really
understand it. Um and then the second
module, the second miniourse will be on
um how to improve, how to tune your
neuronet networks. So you may have heard
that when you're training a neuronet
network, there are a lot of parameters
or we call them hyperparameters.
Hyperparameters are parameters that
control the parameters, right? So the
weights are parameters. Hyperparameters
are things like the learning rate or
what's the size of your neuronet
network. And so there are actually a lot
of hyperparameters that we end up tuning
and um try to give you a way sense of
what are the most important ones and
practical skills for tuning them. It
turns out that um if I look at you know
like my PhD students I think every one
of them that right well I think I think
that probably every one of them
definitely everyone that every PhD
student I know that became great I think
um at some point wound up at 2 a.m.
tuning hyperparameters right um and I
still have very clear recollections of
like being in the office you know 2 a.m.
3:00 a.m. filling with parameters, try
to get it to work. And it turns out that
literally your skill at tuning
hyperparameters, it really makes a
difference. So there were some evenings
that I knew my skill at tuning
hyperparameters, you know, frankly, it
made the difference between whether I
went home to sleep at 3:00 a.m. versus
where I went home to sleep at 7:00 a.m.
Maybe this is not maybe don't do what I
do. I'm not encouraging this type of
behavior. uh but but this is just my
personal experiences but it really makes
a big difference your practical skill at
how quickly you can figure out the
recipe to get these neuronet networks to
train. Um uh and um
and related to that is um
one thing we've chatted a lot about in
this course is strategies for building
machine learning projects.
So it turns out that if you build a
complex system you know let's say you
build this is one example we'll go
through later this quarter. Say you want
to build a system that um recognizes
your face, a camera that recognizes your
face, your friend's face, unlock a door,
right? Security, safety, whatever.
Build. So system like that, you know, I
I've worked on systems like that. Chance
work that these are complex systems with
multiple components. Um there's a camera
there, you know, do you subtract clean
up the image? Do you cut out the face?
How do you register the face? How do you
compare a face? How do you decide to
take another picture before you unlock
the door or just you know or someone
trying to fake hold up a picture printed
on a piece of paper? There actually a
lot of decisions. And so what I find is
that um the biggest difference between a
team that knows how to drive forward a
project like this well and get it done
in days rather than weeks or weeks
rather than many months is the ability
to drive a disciplined development
process. It turns out when you have a
complex system, less experienced teams
will often almost pick things at random
to work on, right? They'll read one
research paper and say, "Oh, I read in
the research paper we should get more
data." You know, well, because like some
newspaper said AI needs lots of data.
So, let's go spend six months to collect
more data. Turns out a lot of the time
collecting more data does not help your
application. Um, but sometimes it's a
huge help. So given your application,
how do you decide? Should you spend more
time collecting data? Maybe you should
buy more GPUs. I I actually definitely
know people that read in the news a lot
of GPUs are helpful, right? And then
I've literally met, you know, fairly
senior business leaders that have um
spent a very large amount of money
buying GPUs and then, you know, um some
funny stories and then and then I go
talk to them and say, "What are you
doing with these GPUs?" And then
sometimes, you know, there was one
meeting I was in where literally a a
very large familyrun business had bought
a lot of GPUs and the CTO
um then pointed to his nephew uh uh who
who who was a who's a current college
student undergrad and said, "Oh, my
nephew knows AI. I'm giving him this
very large budget in GPUs and I think
he'll do AI for me." Right? And so, but
so I think that uh uh knowing how to
make these decisions and not just buying
into the hype that you read about in the
newspapers is is really important. Um
and one thing I hope to do in this
course is share with you what driving a
disciplined development process looks
like because this is one of the things
that really makes a 10x difference in
the speed with which you can get
something to work. Um I I I've literally
seen teams, you know, like take six
months or 10 months pursuing an approach
that experienced engineers would go in
and go, you know what, I could have told
you six months ago that spending all
this time collecting data, this was not
going to get your application to where
you wanted to go, right? Um but so how
do you examine an application and figure
out the diagnostics to figure out what
are the productive things to do for your
application? We actually spend a lot of
time on that. And in fact, um, I'm
excited about doing some simulation
exercises in this classroom with you
later this quarter where, um, I'll
invite you later this quarter, you know,
to to to say in this in this scenario,
what would you do and and see if you
could, you know, make decisions in a
more systematic way, right? Um,
all right.
Um, then course four, we'll talk about
con convolutional networks. Um
very useful for computer vision
applications. Um and then
so connets are specialized models most
you used mostly for uh vision
applications dealing with images and
then we'll talk finally about sequence
models.
So sequences could be time series or
sequences of text uh like words. to also
touch on the transformer network uh that
you know that power a lot of the gen
revolution. Okay. Um and so throughout
learning through learning all of these
things I hope that you gain a large tool
chest um that enable you to tackle an
almost bewildering range of
applications. I think one of the things
I've most enjoyed as a AI person is it
turns out when you work on AI, there are
so many other teams that um have data
and that could use our hope, right? So I
feel like as an AI person, you know, I
somehow bizarrely had a right to play
in, you know, building autonomous
helicopters or hoping companies, I don't
know, place more relevant ads. maybe not
the most inspiring thing I've worked on
but certainly very lucrative for some
companies right or improve web search
rankings um or improve safety uh you
know get rid of the kind of negative
toxic results you may not want search
results to come back on or improve
e-commerce retailing or improve speech
recognition um or help ships be more
fuel efficient right there all these are
real examples um or fight fraud which is
actually really exciting when you're
fighting financial fraud um which is
obviously a bad thing but uh uh when you
sometimes you when you're fighting
fraud, sometimes you wake up in the
morning and your team's alerted you that
there's a new scam and then you just
have to go and fight them and build
algorithms in real time and you know
that every hour you take you know more
more money actually least of the
financial system. So it's kind of awful
that this financial fraud but it's
actually one of the most exhilarating
things I've worked on because literally
every hour you are slower to to you know
formulate response you know more dollars
are leaking out every hour. So um anyway
so so somehow when you have this tool
set of deep learning um you just have a
bewildering right to play or ability to
play in a huge range of applications uh
that could use your hope right and I
think on campus too there's so many
departments um uh across campus um in
the sciences engineering humanities
business uh that have interesting data
where your skill set will let you if you
choose collaborate with them to do
interesting projects and and I find for
example bizarrely
uh some of my PhD students are working
on climate science it's like what do I
know about climate science right I wish
I knew more but using machine learning
tools you know we could actually work on
climate modeling and and geoengineering
and and just play in all of these
important um uh uh important hopefully
important and interesting places I hope
that you have that skill set as well by
the end of this quarter. Yeah.
>> If you have enough data for network
versus like it's better suited for other
like machine learning.
>> Yeah. So how do you know if enough how
do you know if you have enough data for
neuronet network? Um it turns out to be
really difficult to know. Uh so if it's
a application that others have worked on
or that you've worked on before then you
may have a sense. So for example, I know
I because I worked on face recognition,
you kind of have a sense if you want to
train a face recognition system from
scratch, having like 50,000 images,
50,000 unique faces is pretty good,
right? Or or so if you worked on it or
if you read the research literature for
something people have worked on, that
would give you a gut sense for how much
data um could be enough to get you
started. Uh but then for um green few
brand new projects that no one in the
world has worked on before um if you
can't find parallel projects are kind of
comparable it could be really hard to
tell and so common advice for completely
um green field sorry green field I mean
a brand new project dissimilar than
things what so for example if someone
has invented a new medical device and no
one has collected this type of you know
blood specimen data before it's really
hard to tell and in that case the most
Common advice is um get a little bit of
data and just try training a model and
the degree to which your initial model
works or does not work that will help
you hone your perspective on how much
data may be needed and you may be
surprised maybe 100 data points is all
you need right sometimes we've been
surprised by that and then sometimes
we've also worked on applications where
you know 100 billion data points later
we're still trying to get a lot more
data um and I I find it really difficult
to
Good question though. Anything else?
Oh, so this is a good time for me to
pause and take questions because uh so
what what I'm going to do is um uh right
what I'm going to do after this is um
switch tracks and talk a little bit
about exciting trends in AI um uh kind
of recent trends in AI that I'm excited
about and how I view the AI landscape.
But so this is actually a good break
point to see if people have other
questions before I talk about some
trends in AI. Anything else?
>> Yeah, please.
>> When you were differentiating between
those different tasks, what were like
the disting?
So I guess um let's see all of these
many of these terms are blurry and kind
of fuzz a little bit into each other but
um when I refer to generative AI um
generative AI is this uh body of work
that um generates text and sometimes
also images sometimes also audio um
using deep learning algorithms in
certain ways. So I think geni refers to
this body of work um with most of the
center gravity on generating text you
know maybe also images and the text
generation algorithms have been mostly
implemented using transformer neural
networks uh train on large amounts of
data you know straight off the internet
and elsewhere so so when I refer to
genai that's I guess uh that's one
particular application of deep learning
models that has given us large language
models like traiki and cloud and gemini
and uh meta the llama and so on. Does
that make sense? Yeah. Cool.
All right. Anything else?
Cool. All right.
So, let me could we go to the slides,
please? One of the nice things about
this class is Ken and I can occasionally
uh just share a few things we're seeing
in the broader world. Hey, while while
doing that, I'm actually curious how
many of you use a um specialized AI
assisted coding tool like cloud code,
cursor, geni, codeex, curts.
Awesome. Almost everyone, but not
everyone. Interesting. Huh. Interesting.
Oh, I thought interesting. Okay, cool.
So, yeah, one of the most exciting
things that's happened in programming is
AI assisted coding. And I feel like um I
personally hope I never ever have to go
back to coding by hand, right? Like it's
just um it's actually interesting. Uh I
often work in coffee shops on the
weekend and a few weekends ago I was
sitting in a coffee shop and sitting
next to me was someone that was you know
coding by hand and looks so strange. I
just asked them what are you doing in a
in a in a in a respectful way you know
uh and it turns out that the that
they're they're doing a homework from
some other university that required the
code by hand um but one of the things I
find exciting is that um uh individual
programmer productivity is much higher
than ever used to be right and maybe I
want to share with you just just one one
one thing what what I see so I find that
in the software work that I do I I maybe
categorize it into two buckets. One is
building quick and dirty prototypes to
see if something works and then
sometimes I you know write production
grade enterprisegrade robust reliable
software that has a scale right. Um and
I find that where AI assisted coding has
made the biggest difference is building
the quick and dirty prototypes. Um
whereas I think actually literally one
of my collaborators um used one of the
agent decoders that I named but I won't
say which one but literally this morning
he sent me a slack message saying sorry
you know this agent coder had a database
migration error and we just wiped out
all of the database records uh for
fortunately for a test application with
like five users uh but but it did
happen. So I find that oh thank you. So
I find that um my use of the agent code
is you know for the production grade
software is more careful whereas for
building quick and dirty prototypes it
kind of um so you're not shipping
software in respon in irresponsible way.
Um quick and dirty prototypes have lot
fewer dependencies. you usually don't
need to integrate with legacy data
infrastructure. And then, you know, I'm
I'm I'm going to say something that I
that that feels like something I'm not
supposed to say, but I but I'll say it
anyway, which is um uh I find that um
when I am running code, I I find that
people often worry about um safety and
reliability of software or security of
software. So one thing I often say to my
teams is um if you're building a
prototype that only runs on your own
laptop and doesn't use any sensitive
information so there's no risk of
sensitive information then unless you
are planning to you know maliciously
hack into your own laptop right the
security requirements can be lower and
so I find that um when building quick
and dirty prototypes um
having a sandbox environment that lets
you operate within it quickly means
means that you can just make a lot of
decisions faster without worrying as
much about scalability or security or
reliability. So long as a sandbox
environment means this stuff isn't going
to get out there or leak information or
create a security loophole. So that that
that's part of what lets us move much
faster.
And so I find that um because of the
speed of prototyping so you can do so in
a responsible way um to pursue
innovative ideas. my teams were
increasingly, you know, try 20 things
and see what sticks and um because I and
and I know that a lot of teams are
lamenting that many proof of concepts
never make it into production, right?
You try something and it doesn't work.
And I know some teams are feeling angst
about that. I actually have a different
view. I think if the cost of a proof of
concept is low enough, then who cares if
you have to do 20 of them and that's a
price for finding the one or two things
that works really well. So one thing you
hear about in this course is both when
when you're building a machine learning
application, you usually don't know
what's going to happen. Um, and there's
specific reason for that. The reason is
the output of a machine learning
algorithm, it depends both on the code
you write as well as on the data you're
training on. And while you control the
code 100%,
you don't really know usually what's
really in the data in the weird and
wonderful data that the world has given
you. So for example work on speech
recognition a lot in multiple companies
in multiple contexts and even now when I
work on speech recognition I'm still you
know sometimes a little bit surprised
that oh this data has people of a
certain accent more than I realize or
people somehow speak faster or boy
there's a lot of background noise when
people use it in a car right so even
though I worked on speech recognition
multiple times oh and actually one
recent example uh application I I was
actually surprised by the number of
background speakers. They talk to us,
they come and talk to a different
person, then they talk to us and then we
get confused, right? So, so I find that
the data that the world gives us is
often weird and wonderful. And so it is
only by building a system that you then
start to discover these things in the
data that lets you make progress. Um and
with a lot of software applications as
well separate from machine learning
applications a lot of what I end up
having to discover is what do users
actually want right so again I control
my code 100% I can write whatever code I
want I control that but you don't get to
control how your users will react to
your system and I find that our ability
to build quick and dirty prototypes
rapidly um both to discover what's in
the data and also to take the users to
see if they like it. That allows us to
drive faster feedback loops than was
ever possible before to then help us
build more and more valuable software,
right? Um and I think um you know I I I
I know that the mantra move fast and
break things, right? Got a bad rep
because it broke things. Um, and I find
that um, some teams took away from this
that we should not move fast, but I
think that's a mistake. So, what I
usually tell my teams is move fast and
be responsible. And um despite all the
hype about you know AI extinction risk
with AI kills all that somewhat bizarre
hype in my opinion I find that when
teams move really fast we can then
implement things test out in a
responsible way and much more quickly
identify problems and fix them. So, I
find that a lot of the most responsible
teams I know, um, teams able to really
get stuff to work really quickly, uh,
they tend to be some of the fastest
moving teams because it's that speed of
execution that lets you finally
implement it, figure out what's in your
data, figure out what users want, and
that's the best way to figure out what
could actually go wrong um to then make
sure things don't actually go wrong,
right? and
somewhat related to that is um
AI coding assistance. Um and I I I
assume you know almost everyone or
everyone in this class knows how to
code. Um uh if you if you are well you
haven't learned to code yet, you
probably might not want to take this
class yet. Um but I find that uh there
have been people including very senior
right business leaders advising others
to not learn to code on the grounds of
AI will automate it and I I want to
share this with you not because I think
you need to learn to code but because I
hope you help me spread the word right
go to all of your friends in other
departments to tell them this advice to
not learn to code I think we look back
on this as some of the worst career
advice ever given um and and the reason
is when coding becomes easier more
people should do it rather than fewer.
So when humanity went from punch cards
to keyboard and terminal that made
coding easier and so more people learn
to code. Um when we went from assembly
language to modern well at that time
modern programming languages that made
coding easier more people learn to code.
I I went back I actually found these
papers on um when uh these articles on
when Coobo very old school programing
language right was invented and there
were actually people that said oh wow
now we have the coobo programming
language coding is so easy who needs
programmers anymore right and and
obviously the opposite happened um from
text editors to then you know AI
assisted coding as coding becomes easier
people should code a lot more um a lot
more people should learn to code. And
the other thing I'm seeing is I I just
add just something that's been on
people's minds. I know that um uh
unemployment of recent computer science
graduates has ticked up. It's higher
than it's been you know compared to I
think the last decade. Um and so I know
that to people learning CS that has
caused some conststonation. So I'm going
to share my view on that. So um it turns
out that what I see in Silicon Valley
and beyond Silicon Valley is we just
can't find enough people with these
skills, right? I know many businesses
that would well I know large businesses
that love to hire a thousand people with
skills in GI and all deep learning and
machine learning but that are struggling
to find people with these skills. Um,
conversely, there are still, you know,
universities
with curricula that has not changed
since has not changed much, right, for
the last like, I don't know, since 2002
before the rise of Genai and so I do see
that many new CS grads, not from
Stanford, but from, you know, around the
country are struggling with finding jobs
because unfortunately that all their
nonAI enabled skill skill set that is
you know not as much in demand right and
maybe just for myself heck today I will
not hire someone I I will not hire a
software engine that doesn't know how to
use AI to help them with coping just it
just doesn't make sense same reason why
I just won't hire someone that uses a
punch card instead of keyboard and
terminal right and and I think when the
world evolved from punch card to
keyboard and terminal people still had
punch card jobs for a while but
eventually the punch card jobs just went
away it just doesn't make sense anymore
so today There are still coding by hand
jobs around maybe some some specialties
some very low-level coding where AI is
not very good. Turns out AI is not very
good at sometimes with GPU programming.
You know, there are some niches with
coding by hand actually still makes
sense. But for building applications
um you know uh so I I I remember a few
months ago now many months ago now where
I interviewed two engineers back to back
one um had not yet graduated from
college but was highly on top of geni
coding. So you know spoke with that
candidate knew how to use AI built proc
quickly. Right after that I also
interviewed someone with 10 years of
experience as a full stack engineer but
whose skill set was exactly the same as
their 2002 skill set had not tried out
any AI assisted coding really good skill
full sack engineer with 10 years of
experience. And it was actually really
clear to me I picked the fresh college
grad where well he had not he was about
to graduate over someone with 10 years
of experience. Right. So I think um uh
making sure you master these skills are
really important and what I'm seeing um
is there is a very large gap that
businesses are having a hard time
filling um for people with these skills.
Um but the demand for the 2022 skill set
software engineering full set engineing
skill set that is not there right um so
so I think um and then in terms of uh AI
assisted coding um I find that CS
fundamentals really are important so in
addition so I know I I I applied someone
fresh college grad over someone 10 years
experience that true
There's actually one other part to this
story which is with with with respect to
all of you about to graduate from
college. The best programs I know are
also not fresh college grad. No
disrespect intended to fresh college
grads. Some are about to graduate from
Stanford. Uh the best programs I know
are really on top of AI assisted coding
and additionally deeply understand
computer science fundamentals. Right? So
it turns out maybe I'll illustrate this
with a quick story. when I was teaching
an online course um my team wanted to
generate background pictures like this
you know just for decoration. So when I
was working on this um this is of course
generative air for everyone. I was
working with a collaborator Tommy Nelson
that understood art history and so my
collaborator um knew the language of
art. He knew the artistic genre
inspiration, the pallet, so he could
prompt midjourney AI image generation
with the language of art and so he could
generate beautiful pictures like these.
In contrast, I don't know art history. I
wish I did like and so all I could do
was go to mid journey or AI image
generation and I type, please make
pretty pictures of robots for me. And I
could never get the control that my
collaborator Tommy could to generate
pictures like these, which is why we use
all of his pictures and none of mine.
Right?
And I'm seeing the same thing in
computer science. Um,
one of the most important skills for the
future is to understand how computers
work and understand how genai and deep
learning and machine learning work so
that you can use the language of AI, use
the language of these tools to tell a
computer exactly what you want so the
computer can do it for you. And there is
actually a huge difference in
performance between you know someone
that's learned to just prompt an LM
without understanding how computers or
how AI really works versus people they
can look at the problem analyze it and
then with AI assisted coding you know
tell a computer how to take the next
steps. Uh which is why I think that um
CS fundamentals is very valuable. CS
fundamentals, machine learning
fundamentals, deep learning
fundamentals. We my I and my teams we
use that knowledge like every day,
right? In in making pretty consequential
decisions, right? So, so I hope that uh
you get that from this class and the
many other classes at Stanford as well,
right? Um, all right. I think I might
leave the rest. There's more I could say
on trends in AI, but I find that um, uh,
AI assistant. Oh, but but one thing I
hope you do really, you know, go to all
your friends in all the departments
across campus and encourage them to be a
builder because the other thing I'm
seeing is um clearly for computer
science professionals, you know, use AIS
coding, no CS fundamentals,
build cool stuff, but for other
disciplines as well um that is not
computer science or not AI, I'm finding
that um you know the education
professional or the climate scientist or
the mechanical engineer, the ones that
know how to build software um are just
more productive and get a lot more done.
And the barrier to entry to AI to coding
is the lowest it's ever been, you know,
in our lives. And so this is a good
time, frankly, for I I I wish every
single Stanford student, right, will
learn to build software with AI
assistance. Uh so I hope you go help
your friends across campus um to master
those skills as well. Okay.
Oh yeah. Any any other questions? Yes.
Go ahead.
>> AI. I've heard a lot of like a lot of
the industry folks talking about how
they would rather hire someone with 10
years of experience who knows just AI as
is like just using coding rather than
fresh undergrad that does come like that
deep understanding of deep learning
machine learning and like AI as
fundamental just because they have more
experience.
Do you see that also?
>> Yeah. So let me rank productivity right
and I'll give you four levels I think um
and again and I say this with a lot of
respect for individuals so if I talk
about productivity is not with any
disrespect or any lack of affection for
anyone or for their work right but I
think you know least productive are
people with no experience and don't know
AI right
one step on top of that is people with
less experience but on on uh uh sorry
one step on top of that is um uh people
with say a decade of experience
but that don't know AI. Um, on top of
that, I would rather take a fresh
college grad that does know AI, but then
even more productive is someone with,
you know, a decade of experience and
also really on top of AI. So, I think
between the two factors, really
understanding AI is very important, but
experience is also important. And so the
best developers I know um we just work
and we just ship code like was no one's
ever done I think even two three years
ago are very experienced developers.
They're also very on top of how to use
the latest AI technologies
please. Oh oh sorry and just one other
thing about the job market. I find a lot
of employers have not yet figured out
how to hire appropriately. This is
contributed frankly a lot of employees
you know if a company has no one that
knows geni how do they even know how to
interview appropriately so that is a
problem that we need to solve as well.
Go
>> ahead.
Like for example I'm thinking of classes
like CS 1071
where we're not encouraged
to
encourage. Is that true of the
fundamentals?
that's
>> yeah boy. So CS17 CS11 are great. Uh so
so do take them if you're considering
them. I find that the fundamentals are
important. Um uh
how do I put it? Yeah, I'm not sure what
else to say other than that. Um, I think
I think honestly Sanford were known for
CS department were known for really I'm
I'm I know I'm biased but I want to say
like probably the best entry level CS
program classes of any university in the
world. I'm pretty biased so maybe
shouldn't say that but I think uh
they're excellent course if you want to
learn the fundamentals in really solid
way and I know the instructors are
routinely thinking about how to update
the curriculum and realities of geni. So
I I think they do an excellent job with
that mix.
piece.
>> How do you define a person know
comparable to person just out the
person?
>> Yeah. How do I define someone that
really knows geni compared to someone
that just use a tool and typic
um I feel like in Genaii there are two
buckets of skill. Um again by the way
deep learning is not geni deep learning
is also a very valuable skill but syni I
think there two things. one is uh I find
it really useful to um know how to use
AI coding assistance that's really
valuable uh uh but having you know kind
of fundamental knowledge helps right you
do that and then the other thing is in
genai there's a number of emerging tools
I'm going to toss some buzzwords okay so
if you don't know what any of these
words mean don't worry about it but but
I think there are emerging tools like um
rag uh retrie generation or how to uh
vector databases how to do evals and
error analysis how build guard rails.
Um, how to use knowledge drops and
interface that with your OM. Uh, maybe
how to do multimodal, how to fine-tune a
model. Um, what else? I'm probably
blanking on something. Oh, how to build
agentic workflows. But I feel like that
these categories of new techniques built
on top of Genai that are um like a
useful bag of tools for building
applications. So when well frankly when
I'm interviewing candidates you know
which still do a fair amount of is is is
for geni row is these skills I I tend to
look for this set of tools as well as AI
assisted coding uh and and then uh yeah
please
>> I don't know if this question is best
poss to you if I'm considering taking
229 230 at the same time both of those
classes are final projects so how would
you recommend thinking about ideas
to pursue Um yeah, so let me just give
one tip about CS causes in general, not
just 229, CS230, which is I encourage
you to think of um AI causes at Stanford
a bit like Pokemon.
You got to catch them all.
But in all seriousness, I think taking
more CS causes in AI, it it is a good
thing to do. Definitely encourage you to
take multiple causes. Uh I think in some
years we've had students do joint
projects where the standard is higher
higher expectations for sure but um that
that that's that's one option to to look
at. Yeah.
>> All right. Go for it.
>> Oh so let's see. 229 and 230 are very
different causes. um 229 well in 229 you
we have live instructors uh doing the
lectures in person rather than online
content so it's not the flip classroom
so in CS230
um we have most of materials prepared
kind of in online videos highly edited
online videos uh and then um uh C I
think the big the other biggest
difference is uh CS229 is more
mathematical theoretical but there's
important math right whereas CS230 is
more practical ical and so I don't know
if we do even one a single maybe we do
like one proof somewhere in the lectures
but we just don't do a lot of math in
CS230 and it's very a lot of machine
learning is very empirical you should
try see what works but have a
disciplined approach for exploring what
works we focus a lot more on that in in
CS230 and 229 covers a lot more
techniques right so there a lot of
machine learning techniques siz learning
learning you know I don't know decision
trees boosting ky's clustering. So CS229
covers a much broader survey of a lot of
machine learning techniques where CS230
is just one thing. Well, deep we go
really deep into deeper